A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 1994-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade 1994-2006 (bulk 2002-2005)
The Library of Virginia
42293 and 42417
59.55 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Secretary of Education, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219. Accession 42293 transferred 5 December 2005 and accessioned on 6 December 2005; Accession 42417 transferred on 18 January 2006 and accessioned on 19 January 2006.
Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
The Secretary of Commerce and Trade oversees the economic, community, and workforce development of the Commonwealth. During the Administraton of Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006) fourteen agencies and boards reported to the Secretary of Commerce and Trade: Board of Accountancy, Department of Business Assistance, Department of Housing and Community Development, Department of Labor and Industry, Department of Minority Business Enterprise, Department of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation, Tobacco Indemnification and Community Revitalization Commission, Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Virginia Employment Commission, Virginia Housing Development Authority, Virginia Racing Commission, Virginia Resource Authority, and Virginia Tourism Corporation.
On 28 December 2001, Governor-elect Mark R. Warner named Michael Schewel as Secretary of Commerce and Trade. Schewel was a former commissioner of the Virginia Housing Development Authority and had previously worked as head of corporate law for McGuireWoods, LLP. Schewel served until the end of Warner's term in January 2006 and returned to McGuireWoods.
Scope and Content
The Records of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade are housed in 104 boxes. The collection is arranged into nine (9) series. Series have been designated for: I. Constituent Correspondence; II. Office of the Secretary; III. Planning and Budget Files; IV. State Agencies; V. Advisory Boards, Council and Commissions; VI. Development Projects and Initiatives Files; VII. Company Files-Prospects and Development; VIII. Governor's Opportunity Fund; and IX. Special Projects-Virginia Economic Development Partnership. These records include agreements, reports, correspondence, memorandums, budget documents, agendas, handouts, invitations, and speeches. This collection documents the work of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade under Governor Mark R. Warner.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Constituent Correspondence, 2001-2006
II. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2006
Subseries A. Records of Secretary Michael J. Schewel, 2001-2006
Subseries B. Records of Deputy Secretary Matt Erskine, 2001-2005
Subseries C. Records of John Sternlicht, 2003-2005
Subseries D. Records of Special Assistant Sarah Cohen, 2002-2005
III. Planning and Budget Files, 2002-2005
Subseries A. Budget Files, 2002-2005
Subseries B. Legislative Files, 2002-2005
IV. Assigned State Agencies, 1994-2006
V. Advisory Boards, Councils and Commissions, 1998-2005
VI. Development Projects and Initiatives Files, 2001-2005
VII. Company Files-Prospects and Development, 1994-2005
VIII. Governor's Opportunity Fund Files, 2001-2006
IX. Special Projects-Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 1994-2002 (bulk 2001-2002)
Contents List
- I. Constituent Correspondence, 2001-2005., Extent: 13.35 cu. ft. (14 boxes) (Box 1-12, 19-20)
  The Constitutent Correspondence series is housed in 14 archival boxes and is arranged numerically by constituent correspondence number (which is roughly by chronological order by last action taken). This series documents constituent correspondence received by the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade during Governor Mark Warner's administration. This series contains correspondence from various constituents to Governor Mark W. Warner, along with a copy of Michael J. Schewel's letter in response, and a page from the people summary database which includes the name, address, and phone number of the correspondent. Each letter in this series contains a unique tracking number assigned by the Governor's Office Constituent Services. Records are arranged by outgoing tracking number. Some of the notable correspondence in this series relates to the following topics: changes in the definition of an animal shelter to include animal foster homes (2002 Senate Bill 260), requests for extensions of unemployment benefits to Virginians impacted by the economic downturn in the aftermath of the September 11, 2001 attacks, requests for assistance with unemployment claims problems, federal disaster aid for agricultural damage caused by drought, and price gouging complaints for commodoties and clean up services after Hurricane Isabel in 2003.
  - 200104-200402, 2001 Dec; 2002 Jan-Mar. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 200458-200839, 2001 Feb; 2002 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 2000090-2001910, 2001 Dec; 2002 Jan-Mar. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2002008-2002982, 2001 Dec; 2002 Jan-Mar. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 2003033-2003613, 2002 Jan-Feb. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 2003614-2003990, 2002 Jan-Mar; May. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2004073-2004948, 2002 Jan; Apr-May. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2005069-2005911, 1999 July; 2002 Jan-Apr; Sept. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 2005362; 2006117, Legal Folder 2001 Jan; June;Sept-Dec; 2002 Mar; Oct. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 2006001-2006300, 2002 Feb-Mar; May. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 2007323-2008276, 2002 Feb-April; July. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 2008360-2009930, 2000 July-Aug; 2001, Sept-Nov; 2002, Jan-Apr. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 2010395-2011971, 2001 Feb; Dec; 2002, Jan-Mar, May. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 2011975-2012943, 2002 Mar-May. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2013063-2013638, 2002 Feb-May. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 2013669-2013885, 2002 Jan-May. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 2014007-2014521, 2002 Mar-Apr. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 2014524-2014945, 1999 Feb; 2002 Jan; Mar-Apr. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 2015016-2015956, 2002 Mar-May. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 2016089-2016149, 2002,Mar-Apr. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 2016243-2016996, 2002, Feb; Mar-June. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 2017010-2018377, 2002, Mar-June. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 2018529-2018949, 1995 June; 2000 Jan; May; July; 2001 Oct; 2002 Mar-May; Sept. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 2019100-2019566, 1999 Dec; 2000 Apr-May. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 2020007-2020942, 2002, Feb; May. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2021016-2021819, 2002, Feb; Apr-May. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 2022213-2022675, 2002, Apr-May. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 2023223-2023660, 2002, Apr-June. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 2023661-2023990, 2002, May-June. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 2024035-2024921, 2002, Apr-May; June-Sept. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2025099-2025914, 2002 May-June; Sept-Oct. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2026018-2026978, 2002 Apr-July. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 2027004-2027569, 2002 Jan; May-July. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 2028183-2030601, 2002 May-July. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 2030621-2030932, 2002 May-July. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 2031010-2031502, 2002 May-July. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 2031509-2031965, 2002 June-July. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2032027-2032547, 2002 June-July. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 2032555-2032953, 2002 June-July. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 2033003-2033337, 2002 Mar; Apr-June; July; Aug. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 2033351-2033984, 2002 June-July; Aug. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 2034029-2034977, 2002 Apr; June-July; Aug; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 2035006-2035437, 1988 Apr July; 1991 Sept; 1994 Dec; 2002 June-July. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 2035478-2035781, 2002 Mar; Apr; July-Aug. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 2035784-2036584, 2002 July-Aug. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 2036612-2036914, 2002 June; July-Aug. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 2037012-2037945, 2002 June; July; Aug. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 2038012-2038996, 2002 May; June; July-Aug. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 2039173-2039942, 2002 July; Aug; Sept. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 2040013-2040997, 2002 July; Aug-Sept; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 2041020-2041850, 2002 June; Aug-Sept; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 2042132-2042552, 2002 Feb; Aug-Sept; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 2042554-2042933, 2002 Aug-Sept; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 2043043-2043991, 2002 Aug; Sept-Oct. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 2044019-2044915, 2002 Sept; Oct. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 2045125-2049067, 2002 July; Sept-Oct, Nov. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - 2049070-2049988, 2002 Feb; Aug; Sept-Oct. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - 2050166-2053918, 2002 May; Sept-Oct. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 2054017-2056472, 2002 June; Aug: Sept-Oct; Nov. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 2056492-2057873, 2002 Sept; Oct-Nov. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 2058068-2058970, 2002 Oct-Nov. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 2059045-2060897, 2002 Sept; Oct-Nov; Dec. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 2061128-2063708, 2002 Oct-Nov. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 2064032-2066925, 2002 July; Oct; Nov-Dec; 2003 Jan; Feb. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 2067171-2067924, 2002 Sept; Oct-Dec; 2003 Jan; Feb. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 2068076-2069919, 2002 Nov- Dec; 2003 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 2070100-2073409, 2002 Oct; Nov-Dec; 2003 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 2074120-2077563, 2001 Aug; 2002 Dec; 2003 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 2078000-2080790, 2002 Dec; 2003 Jan-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 2080841-2083343, 2002 Dec; 2003 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 2083378-2087499, 2003 Jan. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 2088033-2090756, 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 2091113-2091952, 2003 Jan-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 2092048-2096661, 2003 Jan-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - 2096793-2099798, 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - 2100428-2104438, 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar; Apr. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 2106115-2107823, 2002 Oct Dec; 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar; Apr. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 2108007-2109841, 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 2110041-2111946, 2003 Jan; Feb-Mar. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 2112005-211568, 2003 Feb-Mar. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 2116419-2117986, 2003 Feb-Mar; Apr. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 2118081-2121389, 2002 Jan 2003 Feb-Mar; Apr. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 2121443-2124990, 2003 Feb; Mar-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 2125000-2127316, 2003 Mar-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 2127603-2130932, 2003 Mar-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 2131182-2133902, 2003 Mar-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 2134008-2137906, 2002 Dec; 2003 Mar-Apr. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 2138367-2140913, 2003 Apr- May. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 2141187-2144602, 2003 Mar; Apr-May. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 2151293-2152989, 2003 May-June; July. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - 2153026-2154999, 2003 Apr-May; June. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 2155009-2156973, 2003 Apr-May; June. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 2157231-2158491, 2003 May-June; July. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 2145106-2145986, 2003 Apr-May. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 2146339-2146998, 1994 Dec; 2003 Apr- May. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 2147000-2148985, 2003 Apr- May. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 2149746-2150806, 2003 Apr-May; June. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 2159009-2159664, 2003 Apr-May; June; Sept. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 2159672-2159888, 2003 June. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 2160008-2162523, 2003 May- June. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 2162596-2164321, 2003 May- June (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 2164322-2166806, 2003 Mar-Apr June. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - 2167270-2168919, 2003 June-July. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 2169104-2170733, 2003 June- July. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - 2171010-2172323, 2003 June- July. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - 2172341-2174998, 2003 June- July. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - 2175015-2176613, 2003 June-July; Aug. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - 2177115-2178999, 2003 Apr-July. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - 2179156-2181578, 2003 June-July Aug. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - 2181614-2184750, 2003 June-July; Aug. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - 2185178-2187873, 2003 June-Aug. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - 2188181-2189954, 2001-2003 July- Sept. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - 2190014-2191972, 2003 July-Aug. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 2192020-2193953, 2003 July-Aug. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 2194255-2196997, 2003 Aug-Sept; Oct. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 2197002-2197972, 2003 July-Sept; Oct. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 2198159-2199956, 2003 June-Sept; Oct. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 2200049-2201935, 2003 Aug-Oct Nov. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 2202037-2205804, 2003 Sept-Oct. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 2205813-2208154, 2003 Sept-Nov; 2004 Jan. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 2208160-2212981, 2003 Sept-Oct; Nov. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 2213062-2214958, 2003 Sept- Nov. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 2215038-2216163, 2003 Sept-Nov; 2004 Jan. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 2216179-2218902, 2003 Oct-Nov; 2004 Jan. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 2219221-2220780, 2003 Oct-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - 2221599-2224976, 2003 Oct-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - 2225255-2228787, 2003 Oct-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 2228809-2230809, 2003 Sept-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 2231217-2234903, 2003 Oct-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 2235260-2236714, 2003 Nov-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 2236737-2238916, 2003 Nov-Dec; 2004 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 2239035-2242865, 2003 Nov-Dec; 2004 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 2243502-2247920, 2003 Oct-Dec; 2004 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 2248286-2253942, 2003 Dec; 2004 Jan-Feb. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 2254007-2256332, 2003 Dec; 2004 Jan-June. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - 2256348-2259924, 2004 Jan-Apr. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 2260524-2264850, 2003 Oct; 2004 Feb-Mar. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 2265423-2269971, 2004 Feb-Mar. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - 2270469-2276509, 2003 Oct; 2004 Feb-Mar. Apr (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - 2277141-2283352, 2004 Mar. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - 2283419-2288874, 2003 Aug; 2004 Mar-May. (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - 2289044-2293742, 2004 Mar-June; Aug. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 2294118-2299980, 2004 Apr-June; July. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 2300888-2307849, 2004 Apr-July. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 2307869-2309857, 2004 Apr-July. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 2323020-2325526, 2004 June-July. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 2326713-2327943, 2004 June- July. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - 2309929-2313581, 2004 Apr-July. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - 2315054-2320030, 2004 Apr-July. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 2320081-2323019, 2004 June-July. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 2328039-2331283, 2004 June-July. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - 2331304-2336302, 2004 June-Aug. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - 2336305-2337905, 2004 June-Sept. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - 2338048-2340816, 2004 July-Sept. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - 2341104-2343003, 2004 July-Aug. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - 2343005-2344542, 2004 July-Aug. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - 2345223-2347486, 2004 Aug-Oct. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 2347503-2349374, 2004 Aug-Sept. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 2349379-2351787, 2004 Aug-Oct. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - 2351804-2355949, 2004 Feb-Oct. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 2356062-2358025, 2004 Aug-Oct. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 2358181-2359660, 2004 Sept-Nov. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 2360056-2364735, 2004 Sept-Nov. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - 2365117-2369912, 2004 Sept-Nov. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - 2370024-2374900, 2004 Oct-Nov. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - 2375319-2379662, 2004 Oct-Dec; 2005 Jan-Feb. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - 2381072-2383948, 2004 Oct; Nov-Dec; 2005 Jan. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 2384050-2385419, 2004 Oct; Nov-Dec; 2005 Jan. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 2385462-2387631, 2004 Nov-Dec; 2005 Jan. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 2388203-2392656, 2004 Dec; 2005 Jan-Feb. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 2393157-2396923, 2004 Sept; Dec; 2005 Jan-Feb. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 2397070-2401043, 2005 Jan-Feb. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - 2401063-2403789, 2005 Jan-Feb. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 22404433-2409979, 2004 Nov; 2005 Jan-Mar. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 2410138-2417905, 2004 Apr; 2005 Jan; Mar. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 2418065-2423977, 2005 Jan-Apr. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - 2424099-2434933, 2005 Jan-Apr. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - 2434945-2439934, 2003 Aug; 2005 Mar-Apr. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - 2394131-2511486 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 2480001-2493932 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - 2461158-2479121 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - 2421319-2460865 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 2511505-2565487 (Box 20, Folder 1)
- II. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2006., Extent: 14.55 cubic feet (36 boxes). (Box 14, 21-55)
  Series is arranged into four subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Records of Secretary Michael J. Schewel, 2001-2006; B. Records of Deputy Secretary Matt Erskine, 2001-2005; C. Records of John Sternlicht, 2003-2005; and D. Records of Special Assistant Sarah Cohen, 2002-2005. The correspondence and documents in this series pertain to many of the Secretariat's agencies and boards, as well as to general economic developement related subjects. The series consists of agendas, agreements, correspondence, handouts, itineraries, memorandum, notes, presentations, reports, speeches, talking points and resumes.
  - Subseries II.A. Records of Secretary Michael J. Schewel, 2001-2006., Extent: 4.85 cubic feet. (Box 14, 21-31)
    This subseries is housed in 12 boxes and is divided into 11 sections: Briefing Binders, Appointments, Cabinet Meetings, Meetings with Congressional Delegation, General Assembly Presentations, Subject Files, Correspondence-Chronological, Correspondence-General, Speeches, Calendar and COOP Certifications.
    Notable documents filed under Briefing Binders include: Report of the Issue Working Group, Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 17 December 2001, prepared by Patt Gottschalk, Adele Johnson, Hugh Keogh, Danny LeBlanc, Martha Moore, Bob Templin and staff member Grant Neely (b21, f3); King William Reservoir Project Decision Memorandum, 2003 (b21, f4); and Transition Briefings from each agency under the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, highlighting budget and key issues, 2002 (b21, f10).
    Notable documents filed under Cabinet Meetings include: Schewel's handwritten notes from Cabinet meetings, 2002-2003 (b22, f4); and cabinet meeting follow-up email's from Chief of Staff Bill Leighty (b22, f7-8).
    Notable documents filed under Subject Files include: Schewel's handwritten notes from meetings he attended, 2002-2005 (b24, f5-6); Secretary of Commerce and Trade's Initiatives, 2002-2004 (b25, f4); and the creation of Secretary of Agriculture, 2002-2004 (b25, f6).
    The Correspondence-Chronlogical division contains copies of all out-going correspondence of Secretary Schewel as well as letters written by the Governor in which the Secretary was copied. Arranged in reverse chronlogical order (2006-2002). Subjects include: Governor's Opportunity Fund grants, Virginia Investment Parternship grants, Virginia Employment Commission, Small, Women, and Minority Business initiative (SWAM), and Virginia Community Development Block Grant Program (VCDBG). Notable correspondence include: memorandum from Schewel to Bob Bloxom, Secretary of Agriculture, highlighting issues with the Virginia Department of Agriculture and Consumer Services, 3 January 2005 (b26, f4); memorandum from Schewel to Governor Mark R. Warner through Chief of Staff William H. Leighty, regarding the Commonwealth's Four-Year Economic Development Strategic Plan, 22 April 2002 (b28, f5); memorandum from Schewel to Chief of Staff William H. Leighty, on status of Avian Flu control, 18 April 2002 (b28, f5); and memorandum from Schewel to Chief of Staff William H. Leighty, on drought conditions in Virginia, 15 April 2002 (b28, f5).
    The Correspondence-General division contains general correspondence, memorandums, and working notes of Secretary Schewell. Arranged in chronological order (2002-2003) and in reverse chronlogical order (2006-2004), the correspondence include: thank you letters to the Secretary for his work on bringing new jobs to local communities who have received funding from the Governor's Opportunity Fund; congratulatory correspondence from members of the business communtiy on Schewel's appointment as Secretary of Commerce and Trade; and correspondence with members of the General Assembly regarding projects implemented by the Secretary of Commerce and Trade. Notable documents include: menorandum to Schewel from Chris Lloyd, former staffer in the Secretary of Commerce and Trade during the administrations of George Allen and Doug Wilder, reviewing Mark Warner's economic development promises, 3 January 2002 (b14, f1); memorandum from Schewel to Bill Leighty, Chief of Staff, listing six controversal issues from the Commerce and Trade Secretariat, 15 April 2005 (b29, f4); and a Summary of Major Issues in 2004 for each Commerce and Trade agency, 29 April 2004 (b30, f4).
    The Speeches division contains prepared remarks delivered by Secretary Schewel at meetings, conventions, conferences and public events from 2002 to 2005. The speeches are primarily in reverse chronological order. However many are not dated; original order maintained.
    - Briefing Binders
      - Governor-Elect Warner and Cabinet, 11 December 2001 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Governor-Elect Warner and Cabinet, 17 December 2001 (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Briefing Book for Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 17 Decmeber 2001 (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - King William Reservoir Project Decision Memorandum, 2003 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Research Material: Alternative Energy and Clean Fuel Research at Virginia Universities, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Research Material: Regional Research and Development Center, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Research Material: Retooling Virginia's Economic Development Incentives, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Research Material: Michigan Bond Project and the Ohio Fuel Cell Coalition, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 8)
      - Research Material: Migratory Birds in the Danube Region, 2005 (Box 21, Folder 9)
      - Transition Briefings, 2002 (Box 21, Folder 10)
      - Virginia Tourism Authority, Report to the Governor on Executive Order No. 6, April 2002 (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Virginia Tourism Authority, Group Tour and Meeting Planners Directory, 2001-2002 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Appointments
      - B-D (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - E-R (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - S-W (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Cabinet Meetings
      - Michael Schewel's handwritten notes from Cabinet meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Meeting with Governor Warner, 19 February 2002 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Meeting with Governor Warner, 25 May 2004 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Cabinet Meeting Agendas and Handouts, 2002 (part one) (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Cabinet Meeting Agendas and Handouts, 2002 (part two) (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Cabinet Meeting Agendas and Handouts, 2003 (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Cabinet Meeting Agendas and Handouts, 2004 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Cabinet Meeting Agendas and Handouts, 2005 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Meetings with Congressional Delegation
      - 2002-2005 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - General Assembly Presentations
      - House Appropriations Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Senate Finance Committee, 2002 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Senate Finance Committee, 2003-2004 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Subject Files
      - General, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Conflict of Interests Act Power Point Presentation, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - DMBE Audit, 2004-2005 (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Referenda Guidelines, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Michael J. Schewel Executive Agreement, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - EVA Progress Reports, 2002 and 2004 (Box 24, Folder 4)
      - Michael J. Schewel's Meeting Notes, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 5)
      - Michael J. Schewel's Meeting Notes, 2003-2005 and undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
      - Schewel Cabinet Work Group on Economic Development, ca. 2002 (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - Security Issues, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 7)